<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Samples: Architecture Overview</title>
        <author></author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section id="overview" name="Architecture overview">
		
		  <img src="images/Architecture_Overview.png" align="center" alt="The sample application and the used frameworks"/>
		  
		  <p>The above illustration shows our sample application. 
                  It is divided into the classical three tiers: <em>Presentation Layer</em>, 
                  which is the interface to the user,
		    <em>business layer</em>, which handles the data objects and modifies 
                    them and <em>Data Layer</em>, which consists of a database that loads
                    and stores data.
		    In our example, the business layer is further divided into: (1) The 
                    <em>service layer</em>, which provides services to the presentation layer, 
                    controls the flow of the application and
		    modifies data objects; and (2) the <em>data access layer</em> which deals with 
                    the communication to the database.</p>
		    
		  <p>The illustration also shows that this sample comes in 3 variations:</p>
		  <ul>
		  	
		  	<li><b><a href="arch-basic.html">Basic:</a></b> In the basic example, the user access the application with a Swing client. The service layer is built upon the popular
				Spring Framework. JDBC Templates (also a Spring Feature) are used to access the database.</li>
		    
			<li><b><a href="arch-medium.html">Medium:</a></b> In the second sample application, the user accesses the application through a web frontend that builds on
			    	the Java Server Faces technology. The persistence layer uses the popular O/R mapping tool Hibernate.</li>
		    
		 </ul>
		 
		 <p>All samples use the core module, which contains the interfaces and the data objects.</p>
		
	</section>
        
    </body>
</document>
